<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The damning nature of rebellion, or, The universal unlawfulness of resistance under pain of damnation, in the saddest sense asserted in a sermon preached at the cathedral of Norwich, May 29, 1685, being the anniversary-day of the birth of His late Majesty Charles II, and of the happy restauration both of him and of the government from the great rebellion / by William Jegon ...</title>
            <author>Jegon, William, 1650-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12308712</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12308712</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 188:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The damning nature of rebellion, or, The universal unlawfulness of resistance under pain of damnation, in the saddest sense asserted in a sermon preached at the cathedral of Norwich, May 29, 1685, being the anniversary-day of the birth of His late Majesty Charles II, and of the happy restauration both of him and of the government from the great rebellion / by William Jegon ...</title>
                  <author>Jegon, William, 1650-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Oliver ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Government, Resistance to --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Damning Nature of Rebellion: Or, The Univerſal Unlawfulneſs of Reſiſtance Under pain of Damnation, in the ſaddeſt ſenſ ASSERTED IN A SERMON Preached at the Cathedral of <hi>Norwich,</hi> May 29. 1685.</p>
            <p>BEING THE ANNIVERSARY DAY Of the Birth of His Late MAJESTY CHARLES II.</p>
            <p>And of the Happy Reſtauration both of Him and of the Government from the <hi>Great Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Jegon,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Kings-College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Swanton Morley</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Oliver,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:59325:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>Aug. 27. 1685.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. Alſton, R. P. D. Hen. Epiſc. Lond. a Sacris Domeſticis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59325:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful FRANCIS GARDINER, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> MAYOR of the City of <hi>Norwich,</hi> And one of His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>NORFOLK.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT the Publication of this Diſcourſe is entirely owing to your earnest ſollicitation, I can ſafely avow to the World, having by me ſufficient evidence of it, I mean your Letter, which, if it were allowable to produce it, would evince more than I appeal to it for, even that I could not without incurring the imputation of rudeneſs, or at least affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed modeſty, decline your request; but I can further Appeal to you, and am ſecure of your atteſtation, that I conſented to it with this condition, that our worthy Dioceſans approbation ſhould be first obtained, which you readily undertook, and have it ſeems effected: And this is what I had to ſay concerning the Publication. As to the ſubſtance of the Diſcourſe I have little elſe to ſay but that I am ſure 'tis honeſt, and I have this convincing evidence of it, that you yourſelf approv'd it, whoſe invincible Loyalty is ſo well known, and known to be ſo well grounded.</p>
            <p>Whether it may do that ſervice you conceive, whatever I wiſh, I am ſure I have too much cauſe to fear, when after ſo many excellent Diſcourſes Publiſh'd to the ſame purpoſe, to prove the abſolute <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of Reſiſtance, and proving it
<pb facs="tcp:59325:3"/>to all the purpoſes of Conviction, we find perſons at this time of day the most notoriouſly guilty of it, that will not at their last dying moments be induced to own it or repent of it, which may ſerve for a confirming evidence of what I urge towards the concluſion of my Diſcourſe, that this ſin of Reſiſtance is ſeldom at all, and ſeldomer truly repented of, and therefore the more to be dreaded as, if not certainly, yet too too probably expoſing to Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But if it may contribute in any the least meaſure to thoſe Ends you may conceive, and wiſh it may, and, it ſeems, hope it will, thoſe excellent Ends you yourſelf with ſo much zeal and conſtancy, with ſuch unwearied diligence purſue, even the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our Sovereign and the ſecurity of the Government, I ſhall think myſelf happy, and thankfully acknowledg it: But however the event be, which is uncertain, if you will pleaſe to interest yourſelf in it, by accepting this Diſcourſe, whereof you occaſioned the Publication, you will very certainly and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently oblige,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Swan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on Morley, <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 10. 1685.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SIR, Your moſt Humble Servant, <hi>WILLIAM JEGON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59325:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ROM. XIII. 2.</bibl>
                  <p>They that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>'Tis true, we have loſt, to the great and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral grief of all good People, the principal ſubject of this days Anniverſary Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, our Late Excellent Sovereign, who was this day wonderfully born, and this day more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſtor'd, or rather (if I may ſo ſay) new-born to his People; we have loſt him indeed, and ſuch is our loſs, ſo very great and ſo juſtly deplorable, that I could almoſt be tempted to laments on this very day of publick feſtivity and rejoycing: And I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume I might very excuſably give way to them, were it not that this loſs is ſo happily repair'd, as there may ſeem to have paſs'd rather an exchange than a loſs, and an exchange rather of Names than Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The Tempers, the Vertue, and the very ſouls of the two Royal Brothers being ſo like, ſo undiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable, that we are ſcarce ſenſible even of a change, but think, or may think that both the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers live as formerly, and, as formerly, act with one ſoul ſtill.</p>
            <p>But be it that we have loſt the main and principal ſubject of this days Annual Joy, yet have we not wholly loſt the ground of it; for this day is Sacred and Memorable, not only for the birth of our late Sovereign, but (as we all know) for his Reſtauration
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59325:4"/>too: Nor his alone, but the whole Nations Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the Churches Honour, I had almoſt ſaid her very Being; for ſhe lay ſo long time buried in the duſt and rubbiſh of Anarchy and Confuſion, that ſhe ſeem'd almoſt forgotten, as though ſhe had never been; and therefore her Reſtauration might not improperly be ſtyl'd her Reſurrection. But howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that be, and whatever the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is for outward ſplendour and beauty of Holineſs, all is the effect of this days Mercy, which ought therefore to be ever ſacred and memorable with us, as 'tis order'd to be by publick Authority. And tho' indeed we have of late had too much cauſe, (ſuch was the will of Heaven) to mourn, yet ſtill this day is ſacred to feſtivity on the whole Nations account, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally on the Churches; and we ought to rejoyce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and humbly and heartily bleſs and praiſe Almighty God on her behalf, and devoutly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly pray for the continuance of that happineſs ſhe was this day reſtor'd to, that Peace may ſtill be within her Walls, and plenteouſneſs within her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces: And this is a Duty incumbent upon all her Children at all times, eſpecially now on this memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable day, and 'tis to be hoped we ſhall be all accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly affected to the ſuiting both our hearts and offices to the Grand occaſion.</p>
            <p>But then we may be allowed to remember, as well from what a wretched ſtate of miſery and confuſion, as to what a glorious ſtate of happineſs and peace we of this Church and Nation were by this days mercy advanc'd, and withal what Principles were ſet on foot, and what Practices made uſe of to bring us to that wretched ſtate, and accordingly to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59325:4"/>the refutation of thoſe, and, as far as in us lies, the prevention of theſe for the future.</p>
            <p>And as to the Church which was moſt concerned in them, notwithſtanding what was hinted of her reſurrection this day by way of alluſion, 'tis to be conſider'd ſhe is not yet Triumphant (God knows<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) but too plainly Militant ſtill, and under Perſecution from the Tongues and Pens of perverſe men, her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries on either ſide of her; and both ſo conſtant in their malicious oppoſition to her, that ſhe ſeems indeed (as ſhe hath been repreſented) the very tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of her Saviour ſuffering between two Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, with this difference ſtill, that both revile her, and but one her Saviour.</p>
            <p>For on the one hand ſhe is tax'd with plain Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſm, or profeſſing the true reform'd Religion, on the other with pretended Popery: Her Enemies on that ſide brand her for Schiſmatical, on this for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian: By thoſe ſhe is twitted with Novelty, by theſe with Antiquity as high up as the firſt working of the myſtery of Iniquity, whenſoever it was.</p>
            <p>But the miſery is, and 'tis really pittyable, that all her proteſting, renouncing and abjuring Popery, will not ſuffice to clear her of it: Not all her Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and repeated Victories by her invincible Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions over all her Adverſaries of the <hi>Roman Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> can either convince or ſatisfie, or at leaſt ſilence her domeſtick Oppoſers, but ſtill ſhe is exclaim'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt as Popiſh, plainly Popiſh in her Government, in her Liturgies, and in her Ceremonies: Yea, her Miniſters, how formidable ſoever, as Adverſaries to the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> or Bulwark to their own, and by the ingenuous of that Church reputed rather not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59325:5"/>
               <hi>Catholicks</hi> than <hi>Hereticks,</hi> as the reſt ſtyle them, are yet at home, by her <hi>true Proteſtant ſticklers,</hi> loudly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Maſquerade,</hi> if not plainly and openly <hi>Popiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for her <hi>Doctrine,</hi> it is, as Reform'd, wholly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to <hi>Popery,</hi> and therefore ſure by no means cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as <hi>Popiſh:</hi> Well, I meddle not with other points of her <hi>Doctrine</hi> now, but I am very ſure it can never be thought either <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Phanatical</hi> in the point of Obedience to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> which is the ſubject of my Text: For this ſhe as clearly aſſerts, as firmly eſtabliſhes, and faithfully and conſtantly practiſed as ever was done in any of the pureſt and beſt Ages of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to give ſome little hints of her oppoſition both to <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Phanaticiſm</hi> in this point: She does not derive her Sovereign's Authority either from the <hi>Pope</hi> immediately, or from the <hi>People:</hi> She does not ſubject him to a <hi>Conclave</hi> or a <hi>Conſiſtory,</hi> or a <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Juſtice:</hi> She does not allow him to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenc'd and depos'd by a <hi>General Council</hi> or a <hi>General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly:</hi> To be cut off by a Knife, nor yet by an Axe: To be poſted out of the World by Powder in Barrels, or Powder and ſomewhat elſe in Blunderbuſſes: Nay, ſhe does not allow him to be ſo much as reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon any pretence whatſoever, <hi>without danger of Damnation in the ſaddeſt ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not tell you at this time of day that there have been <hi>Doctrines</hi> currently vented, and practiſes ſet on foot exactly agreeing to them, but both as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>Church;</hi> yea, and of the whole <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> too, for a thouſand years at leaſt, as any thing can poſſibly be: It may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59325:5"/>ſeem very ſeaſonable, upon ſuch an occaſional meeting as this, to enquire what the <hi>Scripture</hi> aſſerts in the Caſe, and ſee whether it does not fully autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> and condemn the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: Accordingly I have choſen a <hi>Text,</hi> the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and ſevereſt againſt <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> of any in the whole <hi>Bible, They that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It has been obſerved from ſundry of the <hi>Antients,</hi> that in the Infancy of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> there was a rumour ſpread (which is ſuppos'd to have taken its riſe from <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> mention'd, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.37.) that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> was deſign'd to undermine Kingdoms and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths; as if indeed the deſign of our <hi>Saviours</hi> firſt coming were the ſame with that which is reſerv'd for his ſecond,
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.24.</note> 
               <hi>To put down all rule, and all authority, and power:</hi> And that for this reaſon our <hi>Saviour</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> did ſo frequently and ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inculcate the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> that the <hi>Religion</hi> might not incur an odium.</p>
            <p>I ſay nothing now to the reaſon alledged, but that both our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did actually inculcate ſo the ſaid <hi>Doctrine,</hi> is obvious to all that are never ſo little converſant in the <hi>Sacred Writings;</hi> and were there no other Inſtances to be produced thence, yet this place of Sr. <hi>Paul,</hi> from whence I have my Text, is ſo plain and pregnant, ſo full and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, as there needs no more to inform and ſatisfie the conſciences of thoſe who are willing to know their Duty, and do not ſeek for cavil or ſubterfuge rather than ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>And ſo fully has this place been canvas'd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd, the Point ſo amply debated, and the Caſe ſo c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>early ſtated from hence, that there can be no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59325:6"/>of ignorance but what is more or leſs wilful, and let us take a curſory view of the context, which begins thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> that is, to the <hi>ſupream Authority</hi> of a <hi>Nation</hi> in whomſoever veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as is unanimouſly agreed on by all unprejudic'd men of ſenſe and learning, and clearly determin'd by the context following; the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Powers,</hi> being afterwards explained by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rulers,</hi> Ver. 3. and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Miniſters of God,</hi> Ver. 4. and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily us'd both by <hi>Claſſic Authors,</hi> and by St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf for ſupream, and ſo render'd by our <hi>Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13.</p>
            <p>To theſe <hi>Higher</hi> or <hi>Supream Powers,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires expreſly that <hi>every ſoul be ſubject:</hi> And here 'tis pertinently remark'd by <hi>Origen,</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> has put his injunction in a term the moſt general and comprehenſive that could be, and yet particularly applicable to every individual, <hi>let every ſoul be ſubject,</hi> as obliging all that have but a common ſoul or ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And our <hi>Church Homilies</hi> are very particular too, and no leſs pertinent in their remark upon this place.
<note n="*" place="margin">Homily of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>pag.</hi> 64. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1673.</note> 
               <hi>We ought diligently to obey St.</hi> Paul, <hi>that dear and choſen Apoſtle of Christ, even as we would obey our Saviour Christ himſelf if he were here preſent; and let us learn of him, that all perſons having ſouls (he excepteth none, nor exempteth none, neither Priest, Apoſtle, nor Prophet,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtom
<note n="†" place="margin">And he ſaith it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed yet more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly: And to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi> and long after both, St. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </note>) do owe of bounden Duty, and even in conſcience, Obedience, Submiſſion and Subjection to the Higher Powers which be ſet in Authority by God: Foraſmuch as they be God's Lieutenants, God's Preſidents, God's Commiſſioners, God's Judges, ordained of God himſelf, of whom alone they have all their Power and all their Authority; and the ſame St.</hi> Paul <hi>threatneth no leſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59325:6"/>pain than everlaſting damnation to all diſobedient Perſons, to all reſiſters againſt this general and common Authority: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as they reſiſt not man but God, not man's device and invention, but God's Wiſdom, God's Order, Power and Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is ſufficiently plain, and this muſt be granted the ſtanding ſenſe of the <hi>Church of England</hi> touching this place of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> becauſe theſe <hi>Homilies,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> contained in them, are eſtabliſh'd by publick <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame in ſubſtance was the current ſenſe of the whole <hi>Church of Christ</hi> in the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>pureſt Ages</hi> of it, and generally of the <hi>Churches</hi> of the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> adds, as the ground or reaſon of this <hi>univerſal ſubjection</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> that <hi>there is no Power but of God: The Powers that be</hi> (or the Powers then in being, for ſo ſome underſtand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo <hi>Nero</hi>'s Power who was then regnant) <hi>are ordained of God.</hi> Can any thing poſſibly be more plain than this for the <hi>Divine Inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Sovereignty?</hi> a thing ſo plain indeed, not only from this and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry other places of <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> but from natural rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon too, that one of the <hi>Antients</hi> affirms,
<note place="margin">Oroſius.</note> they who have not read the <hi>Scriptures</hi> do think it (as very many Learned <hi>Heathens</hi> have declar'd they did) and they who have read them do know it. And in no one point of <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine</hi> have the <hi>Antient Sages</hi> of our <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> the <hi>Primitive Fathers,</hi> more unanimouſly agreed, as the Unlearned as well as the Learned know at this time of day: And all the <hi>Churches</hi> of the <hi>Reformation</hi> are clear for it, as appears from their <hi>Confeſſions.</hi> And for our own <hi>Church,</hi> yea, and <hi>State</hi> too, for I may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyn them together in this, they are as expreſs for it as the plaineſt words can ſhew them to be:</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59325:7"/>
            <p>The <hi>Common Lawyers</hi> agreeing in it with the <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Statutes</hi> as plainly and fully aſſerting it as the <hi>Canons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if there were nothing elſe to prove it, yet the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Sword,</hi> or the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> which is an <hi>eſſential branch</hi> of <hi>Sovereignty,</hi> undeniably evinces it to be <hi>originally</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> who alone could give the ſaid <hi>Power;</hi> and I would fain ſee it prov'd, that the King-creating <hi>People</hi> ever had this <hi>Power:</hi> And if they never had it themſelves, how they could impart it is ſomewhat myſterious.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding ſo general and unanimous a conſent both of <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> as well <hi>Antient</hi> as <hi>Modern,</hi> in a point ſo very plain from the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and in a manner ſelf-evident, great numbers in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> eſpecially, aſſert the contrary, and therein are followed by the <hi>generality</hi> of our <hi>Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts, That all ſupream Power is originally and radically ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the People, and that if Kings fail of their Duty, the People may ſupply it; at leaſt in ſome Caſes may do it of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: That Kings are accountable to the People as their Superiors, and not only cenſurable and puniſhable, but as they are pleas'd to expreſs it,</hi> Dethronable.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſtand to diſpute the Point with them now, but bating the invincible evidence to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of this from the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Sword,</hi> wherewith <hi>Sovereign Princes</hi> are inveſted, I ſhall only put this <hi>Query,</hi> Whether more deference in point of credit and authority be due to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the moſt eminent <hi>Divines</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in all <hi>Ages,</hi> and theſe back'd with the concurrent ſenſe of all ſober <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> or to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Jeſuits</hi> in this point, and without more ado I ſhall leave it to you</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59325:7"/>
            <p>I have hitherto inſiſted upon the <hi>Context,</hi> and ſhewn how it has been (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſignifi'd of old, concerning ſome other paſſages of our <hi>Apoſtle</hi>) wreſted by (the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned</hi> and <hi>unſtable</hi> ſhall I ſay? yea, rather by) the <hi>malitious</hi> and <hi>ſeditious</hi> to their own <hi>deſtruction,</hi> eternal, 'tis to be fear'd; and how juſtly to be fear'd, will appear by enquirng into the <hi>Words</hi> I have choſen for my <hi>Text,</hi> which are as plain and expreſs againſt <hi>reſiſting,</hi> as the <hi>Context</hi> for obeying the <hi>Higher Powers, They that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>Words,</hi> as they ſtand in our <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> are plain indeed, but as they are in the <hi>Original,</hi> they are more liable to <hi>cavil</hi> and <hi>exception,</hi> and then 'tis not to be expected they ſhould eſcape it, when there have been, in ſundry <hi>Ages,</hi> ſo many whoſe <hi>Interest</hi> it was to make it, in order to the ſucceſs (I mean) of their <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Attempts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the <hi>Term</hi> of <hi>reſiſting</hi> there is not much exception made, for tho' it may ſometimes ſignifie no more than to act contrary to the <hi>Command</hi> of the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> yet it cannot bear that ſignification in my <hi>Text,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> may poſſibly command that which we are oblig'd, by a <hi>Power Superiour</hi> to theirs, to act contrary to, as if they <hi>Command</hi> any thing repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the expreſs <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> then as St. <hi>Peter</hi> has determin'd the caſe, and as 'tis <hi>univerſally</hi> agreed on, we ought to <hi>obey God,</hi> and not <hi>Man;</hi> not any <hi>Human Power</hi> whatſoever, but to act contrary to their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand:</hi> And that, for certain, is not to incur <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> of which the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly capable. But to <hi>reſist</hi> (as the very <hi>Words</hi> uſed by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here plainly import) is to uſe <hi>hoſtile vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> or <hi>forcibly</hi> to withſtand, and that is to incur <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59325:8"/>according to our rendring the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> uſes in the <hi>Text;</hi> but whether the word does really import here <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> that is, <hi>eternal Condemnation</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> or only ſome <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Mulct</hi> or <hi>Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate, Whether it be unto Death, or to Baniſhment, or to Confiſcation of Goods, or to Impriſonment,</hi> hath been, and ſtill is, made a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: And truly I have not ſeen any determination of it ſo clear,
<note place="margin">Author <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonymus.</hi>
               </note> as it ſeems to me capable of. A learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, of the late times, hath told us indeed, <hi>That the Analogy of the place will ſufficiently evince the Point, that this word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is like a ſword with two edges, fitted not only to kill the Body, but to deſtroy the Soul alſo; that it threatens puniſhment from the Magiſtrate, is very true, but not all: Ye must needs be ſubject, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake. You are exhorted not to Rebel, becauſe you may be Hang'd: But lest confidence in Numbers ſhould anſwer this Objection, a ſtronger motive is us'd, You ſhall certainly be Damn'd. It is probable you may take the Gallows in your way, but, however, Hell will be the end: Yea, though you eſcape a ſhameful Death, yet you have forfeited eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be ſo, as this <hi>Author</hi> ſays, and indeed it is too probable, but he has not clearly evinced it.</p>
            <p>Some have gone further, and ſaid much more, but I conceive not all that might be ſaid upon it: And of late, in <hi>popular Diſcourſes,</hi> it has been rather taken for granted, than deſignedly proved. I humbly offer, therefore, the reſult of my <hi>Meditations</hi> upon the <hi>Point,</hi> and upon the <hi>Text,</hi> and I ſhall do it in this method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall endeavour to prove, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place, does really ſignifie <hi>Damnation in the ſaddeſt ſenſe,</hi> that is, <hi>eternal Condemnation</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> tho' not excluding the other more <hi>gentle ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:59325:8"/>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall ſhew that there is nothing to take off the <hi>force</hi> of this <hi>intermination,</hi> no juſt caſe of <hi>exception</hi> againſt the rule of my <hi>Text,</hi> no <hi>pretence</hi> allowable; but for <hi>Subjects</hi> to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> I mean, forcibly to <hi>reſist</hi> their <hi>Lawful Sovereign,</hi> is <hi>abſolutely</hi> and <hi>univerſally</hi> to incur <hi>Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and nothing to <hi>atone</hi> for the <hi>Crime,</hi> in the ſight of <hi>God,</hi> or to prevent the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> threatned here, but <hi>Repentance.</hi> And this is all I can think neceſſary to inſiſt upon from the <hi>Words,</hi> ſaving only ſome little matter by way of <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place, does realy ſignifie <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, 'tis granted, the <hi>Word</hi> does ſignifie, in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Human Judgment,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Capital Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi> or the <hi>Sentence</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> inflicted upon <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors:</hi> But then it muſt be granted too, that, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> it ſignifies <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Puniſhment,</hi> or <hi>Damnation in the ſaddeſt ſenſe:</hi> And that not only where it is joyned with other words, that plainly point and direct to that <hi>ſenſe,</hi> but where it ſtands by it ſelf alone, without any additional <hi>note</hi> or <hi>point</hi> of <hi>direction:</hi> And this hath been ſhewed at large by learned men,
<note n="*" place="margin">Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly Dr. <hi>Hammond, in loc. &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libi.</hi> and Dr. <hi>Falken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Loyalty. Part 2.</note> and ſo need not be ſtood upon now.</p>
            <p>But this being taken for granted, that more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the <hi>Scripture</hi> uſes the <hi>Word</hi> for <hi>Damnation in the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest ſenſe,</hi> the only queſtion is, <hi>Whether ſo here in my Text, or no?</hi> I do not ſay <hi>excluding,</hi> but <hi>implying</hi> the <hi>other ſenſe</hi> too of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is, indeed, another remarkable place where the <hi>Word</hi> is uſed, but in what <hi>ſenſe,</hi> is alike queſtion'd; and that is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. where it is applied to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Communicants: He that eateth and drinketh unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59325:9"/>eateth and drinketh</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we read, <hi>Damnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> But whatever the <hi>real ſenſe</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be there, it has been very pertinently obſerv'd, that in the <hi>late un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy times,</hi> when the queſtion was moſt ſtifly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſs'd about the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of my <hi>Text,</hi> moſt of thoſe who were hotteſt for the <hi>gentler ſenſe</hi> in the place of my <hi>Text,</hi> as making for their <hi>Intereſt</hi> who were <hi>actually</hi> in <hi>Arms</hi> againſt their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and little fear'd any <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Puniſhment,</hi> were as hot for the <hi>ſadder ſenſe</hi> of the ſame <hi>Word</hi> in that other place to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> And the reſult was, that effectual care was taken men ſhould not incur <hi>Damnation</hi> for <hi>Communicating unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> by keeping them from <hi>Communicating</hi> at all, for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years together.</p>
            <p>But then, that men might not be as much deterr'd from <hi>reſiſting,</hi> or <hi>taking</hi> up <hi>Arms</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>continuing</hi> in them, by any <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifying <hi>Damnation</hi> indeed in this place of my <hi>Text;</hi> it was eagerly contended for the <hi>gentler ſenſe</hi> to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix'd to this place, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here ſhould ſignifie only ſome <hi>Temporal Puniſhment,</hi> which the <hi>King</hi> might <hi>inflict,</hi> if he happened to <hi>Conquer</hi> his <hi>Rebels</hi> up in <hi>Arms</hi> againſt him: And if it ſhould come to that once, then men were to look to themſelves, and ſcape as well as they could.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>reſiſting,</hi> or <hi>taking</hi> up <hi>Arms,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Againſt the King.</note> would be plain down-right <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and of a moſt <hi>horrid nature,</hi> but not 'till then, according to <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s <hi>Doctrine,</hi> who, in the midſt of the <hi>late War,</hi> declar'd, (it ſeems) <hi>That if he and his Party prevail'd, their oppoſers would be accounted the grandest Traytors, to the State, that ever were: But if the King ſhould prevail, their undertaking would be judged the most horrid and black Rebellion that ever the Sun beheld.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59325:9"/>Then have a care of <hi>Attainders</hi> and <hi>Executions,</hi> of <hi>Gibbets</hi> or <hi>Axes, Confiſcations</hi> or <hi>Impriſonments;</hi> but no beware of <hi>Damnation</hi> all this while: No, that was no part of their <hi>care</hi> or <hi>fear,</hi> and, indeed, <hi>Why ſhould it?</hi> If <hi>taking</hi> up <hi>Arms</hi> againſt their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> were neither <hi>threatned,</hi> nor like to be <hi>attended</hi> with any worſe <hi>conſequence,</hi> than only ſome <hi>Temporal Mulct</hi> or <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> which were certain to be avoided by <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> if that were the <hi>iſſue:</hi> Or, if the worſt ſhould happen, it were more than poſſible to be avoided by <hi>flight</hi> or <hi>concealment,</hi> or perhaps by the <hi>clemency</hi> of the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> or at leaſt the number of <hi>Reſiſters</hi> would ſecure the far greateſt part from the utmoſt <hi>ſeverities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when there was ſo many <hi>ſtarting holes,</hi> ſo many, (<hi>poſſible,</hi> ſhall I ſay? nay,) <hi>probable</hi> ways of <hi>eſcaping</hi> this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> in <hi>their ſenſe</hi> of it, who would needs have it import only ſome <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> Why ſhould they fear <hi>reſiſting</hi> or <hi>taking</hi> up <hi>Arms,</hi> or <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing</hi> in them, and not rather go on to <hi>fight manfully the Lords Battels, and help him against the mighty;</hi> when they were ſo far from incurring <hi>Damnation</hi> for it, that they were plainly <hi>accurſed</hi> if they did not, as they were <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently</hi> and <hi>roundly</hi> told from that
<note place="margin">Jer. 48 10.</note> place of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> wretchedly miſ-applied: <hi>Curſed is he that doth the work of the Lord deceitfully,</hi> or negligently, <hi>and curſed is he that keepeth back his ſword from blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, to recollect my ſelf, though what has been now ſaid cannot favour much of digreſſion, becauſe the <hi>Tenets</hi> and <hi>Practiſes</hi> ſpecifi'd, are plain natural reſults from the premiſes laid down: For if to <hi>reſiſt</hi> be not to incur <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> but <hi>barely</hi> and <hi>ſimply</hi> ſome <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Mulct</hi> or <hi>Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and that too not <hi>certain,</hi> not <hi>inevitable,</hi> and far from that, What ſhould hinder <hi>reſiſting</hi> at any time upon a <hi>proſpect</hi> of <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> or at leaſt a <hi>conſiderable advantage?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59325:10"/>
            <p>But, God be thanked, the caſe is not altogether ſo clear for them, for 'tis certainly poſſible, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place, may ſignifie <hi>Damnation in the ſaddeſt ſenſe,</hi> as it does confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly in ſundry other places of <hi>Holy Writ;</hi> and, if it were only ſo, <hi>Reſiſters</hi> cannot be altogether <hi>ſecure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to reſt here, I ſhall forthwith betake me to the clearing my firſt <hi>Propoſition,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place of my <hi>Text,</hi> does really ſignifie <hi>Damnation in the ſaddeſt ſenſe:</hi> And this I ſhall ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Context</hi> or the <hi>Analogy</hi> of the place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the <hi>current ſenſe</hi> of the moſt approved <hi>Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors;</hi> and,</p>
            <p n="3">3. From parallel places of <hi>Holy-Writ,</hi> which repreſent <hi>Reſiſting</hi> as a <hi>Crime</hi> of a moſt <hi>groſs horrid Nature,</hi> and <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, damning in the ſight God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſhew it from the <hi>Context</hi> or the <hi>Analogy</hi> of the place.</p>
            <p>And here, 1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> is plainly the <hi>Precept</hi> eſtabliſh'd upon this <hi>Penalty,</hi> whatever it be that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> imports; and we are pretty well agreed about the <hi>Notion</hi> of the <hi>Higher Powers:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I have prov'd already that it <hi>ſignifies</hi> the <hi>ſupream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of a <hi>Nation,</hi> in whomſoever veſted. That we be <hi>ſubject</hi> to this <hi>Authority,</hi> is an <hi>Apoſtolical Precept;</hi> and our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> has expreſly given the ſame <hi>Authority</hi> to his <hi>Apoſtles Doctrine,</hi> as to his <hi>own</hi> delivered by <hi>himſelf,</hi> and commanded them to be received with the ſame defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of <hi>belief</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſion,</hi> as what they deliver in point of <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Precept</hi> as <hi>himſelf: He that receiveth you, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me, and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that ſent me,</hi> St. Matt. 10.40. And, as it was intimated before, as the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> we ought to obey St. <hi>Paul,</hi> even as we would obey <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf: And ſure, from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59325:10"/>what has been ſaid, 'tis plain we ought. Whatever then the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> deliver, as the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> is <hi>Goſpel</hi> as much as any thing <hi>Recorded</hi> by the four <hi>Evangeliſts:</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is very plain for this, <hi>That all who obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall be puniſh'd with everlaſting deſtruction,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.8, 9. <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> is here expreſly injoyned by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently is a <hi>Goſpel Precept:</hi> And notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s nicety of a <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> not contrary to <hi>ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> certainly all <hi>forcible Reſiſtance,</hi> which is plainly the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> meaning here, is ſufficiently contrary to <hi>ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Now, whether to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to <hi>diſobey</hi> the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> be not to incur <hi>everlaſting Deſtruction,</hi> or <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> I leave to be conſider'd.</p>
            <p>Again, 2. All <hi>Power,</hi> and by a neceſſary conſequence the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> are of <hi>Divine Inſtitution:</hi> This is expreſly aſſerted by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here, <hi>There is no Power but of God: the Powers that be, are ordained of God:</hi> And thence he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, <hi>That whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God.</hi> Now, whether to <hi>reſiſt</hi> a <hi>plain Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> an <hi>inſtitution founded</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> if we will take the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> word for it, be not to offer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to the <hi>ſacred Authority</hi> of <hi>God</hi> himſelf, and ſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur his <hi>final diſpeaſure,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> without <hi>Repentance,</hi> I leave again to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> adds here, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. of this <hi>Chap. Ye must be ſubject, not only for wrath, but alſo for conſcience-ſake:</hi> Here by <hi>wrath,</hi> all the World underſtands <hi>Temporal Puniſhment:</hi> And, as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> hereupon urges, if that were all that is meant by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Text,</hi> it could not be true, much leſs concluded thence, <hi>that men must be ſubject, not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59325:11"/>only for wrath;</hi> but if we muſt needs be <hi>ſubject,</hi> and by, at leaſt, an <hi>equal neceſſity,</hi> not <hi>reſist, not only for wrath,</hi> or for fear of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment,</hi> then he that does <hi>actually reſist,</hi> ſhall <hi>receive</hi> or <hi>incur</hi> more than a <hi>Temporal Puniſhment,</hi> even all the <hi>conſequence</hi> of a <hi>mounded, grieved conſcience,</hi> which, when it <hi>accuſes,</hi> binds over to <hi>eternal wrath,</hi> or <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> without <hi>repentance,</hi> as no man doubts, that <hi>pretends</hi> any <hi>acquaintance</hi> with the <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine.</hi> If therefore we will allow the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to ſpeak <hi>ſenſe</hi> here, we muſt grant there lies on us, from theſe <hi>words,</hi> a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>ſubjection,</hi> and conſequently of not <hi>reſiſting</hi> for ſome <hi>higher</hi> and <hi>further reaſon,</hi> than only a <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and what that can be other than <hi>eternal,</hi> or <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> I leave again to be conſider'd.</p>
            <p>But here it is urged bo way of <hi>Objection,</hi> and that from the <hi>Context</hi> too, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place, muſt ſignifie only ſome <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> becauſe it follows immediately, <hi>Rulers</hi> are not a terror to <hi>good Works,</hi> but to the <hi>evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the way, their <hi>Objection</hi> plainly implies, that to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist</hi> is an <hi>evil Work,</hi> or elſe it were not <hi>puniſhable</hi> by the <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> and as ſuch it is, as all other <hi>evil Works</hi> are, not only a <hi>ground</hi> of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment,</hi> but expoſes Men to <hi>Eternal,</hi> without <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to anſwer directly to the <hi>Objection;</hi> 1. It is not deny'd, but <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> is a matter which the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> is concern'd to <hi>puniſh;</hi> and they that <hi>actually reſiſt</hi> him, may ſecure themſelves: he will <hi>puniſh</hi> them for it, if it be in his <hi>power,</hi> and he be not ſome way <hi>appeas'd,</hi> or otherwiſe <hi>prevented.</hi> But who can perſuade himſelf, that the <hi>Bleſſed Apoſtle,</hi> by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> directing him, ſhould threaten ſo great a <hi>Crime</hi> as <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> which is no better than <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and that is as the ſin of witchcraft,</hi> with an award
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59325:11"/>which is common to it, with the <hi>meaneſt offences</hi> in the <hi>World?</hi> nay, that the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Learned Apoſtle</hi> ſhould ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue againſt <hi>reſiſting</hi> from ſo poor a <hi>Topick,</hi> as fear of <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Puniſhment</hi> only, ſeems to me ſo <hi>jejune</hi> and <hi>flat,</hi> as is infinitely below his <hi>Character,</hi> as the great <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> He needed not his Education at the feet of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel,</hi> much leſs his <hi>Infallibility</hi> as an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to dictate this, for certainly <hi>Nokes</hi> or a <hi>Styles,</hi> a <hi>Cade</hi> or a <hi>Kett,</hi> or any of the <hi>Rabble</hi> of <hi>Reſiſters,</hi> need not be told that they incur a <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> if they be <hi>ſubdued</hi> and <hi>taken</hi> in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> or <hi>deprehended</hi> in the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> or <hi>Deſign</hi> of it. But if they happen to <hi>ſubdue</hi> or <hi>awe</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or ſome way or other to <hi>eſcape,</hi> as 'tis odds but they may, at leaſt the more inconſiderable among them, What ſignifies the <hi>intermination</hi> of the <hi>Magiſtrates Anger,</hi> and the <hi>conſequence</hi> of it, ſome <hi>Temporal Puniſhment,</hi> to <hi>deter</hi> them from <hi>reſiſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, If fear of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> were the ſum of the <hi>Apoſtles Argument</hi> in this place, Why ſhould he particularly apply it to the inſtance of <hi>reſiſting?</hi> the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate</hi> might be ſaid indeed not to <hi>bear</hi> the <hi>ſword</hi> altogether in <hi>vain,</hi> if he did <hi>bear</hi> it only againſt <hi>Treaſon, Rebellion,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>violations</hi> of <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately concern his own <hi>Perſon:</hi> But certainly he could not be ſaid to <hi>bear</hi> it to any great purpoſes of <hi>advantage</hi> to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> or <hi>Community</hi> of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> if he did not <hi>bear</hi> it againſt other <hi>Criminals</hi> and <hi>Malefactors</hi> as well as againſt <hi>Reſiſters</hi> or <hi>Traytors,</hi> and if equally againſt all, Why the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhould alledg the <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>danger</hi> of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Reſiſters</hi> only? if that were all he meant, I am very much to ſeek; and therefore, methinks, for the honour of the <hi>Apoſtle, Chriſtians</hi> ſhould not preſume to <hi>father</hi> ſo <hi>trifling</hi> an <hi>Argument</hi> upon him, as that if any <hi>reſiſt</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:59325:12"/>the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> they ſhall receive a <hi>Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> If we underſtand the <hi>merit</hi> here, and not the <hi>event,</hi> that <hi>reſiſters</hi> deſerve a <hi>Temporal Puniſhment,</hi> 'tis very true indeed, but to no great purpoſe of <hi>deterring</hi> them: If the <hi>event,</hi> it will not always hold, for certain, it will not in the ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of a <hi>proſperous Rebellion,</hi> or <hi>flight,</hi> or <hi>conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or ſome other way of <hi>avoidance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to ſum up what has been ſaid upon this firſt <hi>Argument</hi> taken from the <hi>Context;</hi> Seeing, 1. It is an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical,</hi> and <hi>conſequently</hi> a <hi>Goſpel Precept, That we be ſubject to the Higher Powers;</hi> and to <hi>reſiſt</hi> them, in the <hi>plain ſenſe</hi> of my <hi>Text,</hi> muſt be <hi>granted</hi> not to be <hi>ſubject,</hi> and not to be <hi>ſubject,</hi> is not to <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and not to <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> is, to incur <hi>everlaſting Deſtruction,</hi> without <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing in the ſecond place, that to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the <hi>Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> is evidently to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and that is to offer <hi>contempt</hi> to the <hi>ſacred Authority</hi> of <hi>God</hi> himſelf, and that can be no leſs than to incur his <hi>final diſpleaſure,</hi> and conſequently, <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> without <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> ſtill.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Seeing we muſt needs be <hi>ſubject,</hi> and, by <hi>conſequence,</hi> not <hi>reſist, not only for wrath,</hi> or for <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> it muſt be for ſome <hi>other reaſon,</hi> or on ſome <hi>further account,</hi> and that is, plainly, for <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>wounding</hi> our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> which will certainly expoſe us to the <hi>wrath eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> without <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, Seeing it were exceedingly below the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to argue againſt <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> from ſo poor a <hi>Topick,</hi> as <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> only, which all the <hi>World</hi> knows will certainly attend the <hi>Crime</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> if not ſome way or other <hi>prevented,</hi> and which might as well be urged againſt any other inſtance of <hi>offending</hi> the <hi>Laws.</hi> I ſhall not make my own <hi>reference,</hi> but leave it as before
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59325:12"/>to be <hi>conſider'd,</hi> whether the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> can <hi>reaſonably</hi> be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to intend by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place, any thing leſs that <hi>eternal Damnation,</hi> without <hi>Repentance,</hi> as the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed to my ſecond <hi>medium,</hi> by which I <hi>propoſed</hi> to prove this, and that is the <hi>current ſenſe</hi> of the moſt approved <hi>Expoſitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I might <hi>urge</hi> what I find <hi>aſſerted</hi> to my <hi>hand,</hi> that not one <hi>Writer</hi> for a <hi>thouſand years,</hi> of any <hi>credit</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> did ever <hi>doubt</hi> or <hi>queſtion</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> as 'tis <hi>maintained</hi> by the <hi>Church of England,</hi> or the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of <hi>reſiſting</hi> them, upon any <hi>pretence</hi> whatever: And why? but becauſe the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> ſo <hi>frequently,</hi> and <hi>particularly</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> here in this <hi>Chapter</hi> has ſo plainly <hi>ſtated</hi> it, made it ſo <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>manifest,</hi> and ſo <hi>formidably</hi> threatned the <hi>oppugners</hi> of it. And for the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> in all parts of the <hi>Word</hi> (which is <hi>incomparably</hi> the beſt <hi>Comment</hi> upon the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi>) 'tis very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they were univerſally <hi>ſubject</hi> to their <hi>Governors, in omnibus licitis,</hi> and never <hi>reſiſted</hi> them, whatever <hi>ground</hi> or <hi>pretence</hi> they might have for it; and this, indeed, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as <hi>univerſally</hi> acknowledg'd that they did not <hi>actually reſist:</hi> Their <hi>Reaſons</hi> we ſhall after enquire into. But take we this by the way, in St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s words; <hi>Their Demeanour was perpetually and invincibly Loyal towards their Temporal Governors, without any the least Reſiſtance,</hi> propter Dominum eternum, <hi>for fear of offending their great and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sovereign, the Lord of Heaven and Earth, and thereby incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his final diſpleaſure, the effects whereof are intolerable and eternal, and altogether unavoidable, but only by Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to be more <hi>particular,</hi> with <hi>reference</hi> to the <hi>Argument</hi> in hand.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59325:13"/>
            <p>Among the <hi>Antients,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and thoſe who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by way of <hi>expounding</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> neareſt the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for the reſt, almoſt all before him, were moſtly given to <hi>Allegorical Expoſitions:</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> I ſay, and his followers, as <hi>Theophylact</hi> and <hi>Oecumenius,</hi> I may add <hi>Photius</hi> too, for ſo much as remains of his <hi>Comments,</hi> are generally accounted the beſt <hi>Commentators.</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (ſays a
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> his Life St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom.</hi>
               </note> Learned Man of our own <hi>Church</hi>) had ſo <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> a <hi>Talent</hi> in <hi>expounding</hi> the <hi>Scripture,</hi> in the moſt <hi>obvious</hi> and <hi>litteral ſenſe,</hi> that, as an <hi>Antient Writer</hi> aſſures us, his <hi>judgment</hi> herein was accounted the <hi>common ſtandard</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and out-weigh'd the <hi>Expoſitions</hi> of all the other <hi>Fathers:</hi> Now he and his <hi>followers,</hi> with one conſent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <hi>plainly,</hi> if not <hi>expreſly</hi> too, for the <hi>ſadder ſenſe</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this place. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom's</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no <hi>light,</hi> but very <hi>ſevere vengeance,</hi> and that from <hi>God,</hi> who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>ſevere avenger</hi> of all ſuch as <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn</hi> theſe <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> and thereby, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly <hi>provoke God,</hi> is ſufficiently clear for my <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe;</hi> and ſo <hi>Theophylact,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he that <hi>reſiſts</hi> ſhall be <hi>puniſh'd</hi> by <hi>God</hi> himſelf: And to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Photius</hi> in <hi>Oecumenius</hi> (whom I may therefore cite as one) expreſly interprets the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Condemnation</hi> from <hi>God.</hi> I deny not but all theſe, how much ſoever they are for the <hi>ſadder ſenſe</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, do withal include the other <hi>ſenſe</hi> too of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> which I know none that <hi>offers</hi> to <hi>exclude,</hi> though I think it not very <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be <hi>urgent</hi> for it, or lay any <hi>great ſtreſs</hi> upon it, becauſe ſo likely to follow in all caſes of <hi>Reſiſting</hi> that are <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous,</hi> and do not <hi>prevail</hi> upon the <hi>Legal eſtabliſh'd Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But be it that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> implied, in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59325:13"/>a <hi>Temporal Puniſhment</hi> from the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> ſo it be <hi>granted,</hi> as 'tis by theſe <hi>Antients</hi> expreſly, that he <hi>meant</hi> by it, and that <hi>chiefly</hi> too, <hi>eternal Damnation</hi> from <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And with theſe of the <hi>Greek Church,</hi> agree St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> for the <hi>Latin.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon thoſe words, <hi>Ye must needs be ſubject, not only for wrath,</hi> id eſt, ultionem preſentem; <hi>that is,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for fear of preſent or temporal vengeance,</hi> ſed &amp; propter futurum judicium, <hi>but alſo for fear of the judgment to come,</hi> quia ſi hic evaſcerint, illic eos poena expectat ubi ipſa accuſante conſcientia punien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: <hi>For however,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they eſcape here, yet there their own conſcience will be their accuſer, and God himſelf their avenger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ep. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> concerning <hi>Reſiſters, that beſides what they may ſuffer from men,</hi> apud Deum fortem non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebunt, <hi>they ſhall have no part with God;</hi> and elſewhere he reckons it very clear and manifeſt: <hi>Patet</hi> (ſays he) <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale peccatum eſſe poteſtati civili reſiſtere,</hi> 'tis evident, that to <hi>reſist</hi> the <hi>Civil Power</hi> is a <hi>Mortal Sin:</hi> And by <hi>Mortal,</hi> we know he means a <hi>Sin</hi> of a <hi>damning nature,</hi> that fearfully expoſes to the <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>indignation</hi> of <hi>Almighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And with theſe conſents St. <hi>Bernard</hi> too, though liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an <hi>Age</hi> when the <hi>Papal Power</hi> had not a little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach'd upon the <hi>Imperial,</hi> but much corrupted the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Doctrine</hi> in <hi>point</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Higher Power:</hi> Yet he, even in that <hi>Age,</hi> aſſerted it <hi>damnable in the ſaddest ſenſe</hi> to <hi>reſist,</hi> and that from this place of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in my <hi>Text</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Ep. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 221. <hi>Ludovic Regem.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>And to come down to thoſe of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality</hi> of them are <hi>clear,</hi> if not for the <hi>ſadder ſenſe</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, yet, which is all one, for the <hi>damning nature of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> even <hi>Paraeus,</hi> who has been <hi>cenſur'd</hi> for ſome <hi>unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed expreſſions</hi> in the <hi>Caſe,</hi> is very <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>right</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in his <hi>Comment</hi> upon my <hi>Text,</hi> not only affiring
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59325:14"/>that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here may be taken in either <hi>ſenſe,</hi> of <hi>Temporal</hi> or <hi>Eternal Puniſhment:</hi> But that however <hi>Reſiſters</hi> may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the hands of <hi>Men,</hi> yet, <hi>Certe a Deo,</hi> from <hi>God</hi> they are ſure of a <hi>ſevere award.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to Contract, the moſt <hi>eminent Divines</hi> of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> though they meddle not with the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in my <hi>Text,</hi> yet they agree in the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of it, <hi>generally</hi> aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it <hi>damnable</hi> to <hi>reſist;</hi> and none, or very few of thoſe that call themſelves <hi>Proteſtant Divines,</hi> are <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in this, but only thoſe of the <hi>Kirk of Scotland,</hi> and their <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> here, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Phanaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and all her <hi>Divines,</hi> or <hi>true</hi> and <hi>regular Sons,</hi> as well as <hi>Fathers</hi> in the caſe, 'tis ſo <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>clear,</hi> and ſo very well known that, it were an <hi>inexcuſable impertinence</hi> to inſiſt <hi>particularly</hi> upon it at this time of day.</p>
            <p>And now being compaſſed with ſo great a Cloud of <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> having ſuch a <hi>concurrent stream</hi> of <hi>Expoſitors</hi> and others on my ſide, I hope I may venture to <hi>aſſert,</hi> from the <hi>importance</hi> of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in my <hi>Text,</hi> that it is a <hi>ſin</hi> of a <hi>damning nature</hi> to <hi>reſist</hi> the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall add to the <hi>Confirmation</hi> of it, from my third propoſed <hi>Topick,</hi> and that is, from <hi>parallel</hi> places of <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> which repreſent <hi>reſiſting</hi> as a <hi>Crime</hi> of a moſt <hi>horrid nature,</hi> or at leaſt a very great <hi>ſin</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently</hi> of a <hi>damning nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I inſtance, 1. In that very <hi>remarkable expreſſion</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to <hi>Korah</hi> and his <hi>Company,</hi> when they <hi>aſſociated</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together againſt him, and were not far from <hi>taking up Arms,</hi> but certainly ſo far <hi>reſiſted</hi> him, as openly to <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> his <hi>Authority,</hi> as an <hi>encroachment</hi> upon them. <hi>Ye are gathered together,</hi> ſays he to <hi>Korah</hi> the Ring-leader, <hi>thou and all thy Company are gathered together against the Lord,</hi> Numb. 16.11.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59325:14"/>
            <p>They were not ſo <hi>ſenſeleſs</hi> as to gather together <hi>intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally</hi> againſt the <hi>Lord;</hi> no, but they were gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> their <hi>ſupream Civil Governor</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo by God, againſt <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>chief</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Adminiſtration:</hi> And this <hi>Moſes</hi> calls their <hi>gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther against the Lord.</hi> And, as Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> obſerves, even <hi>Women</hi> did ſee plainly that in oppoſing <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in ſuch a manner, they oppoſed <hi>God</hi> himſelf, the <hi>ordainer</hi> of their <hi>Authority,</hi> for ſo the Daughters of <hi>Zelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phehad,</hi> Mumb. 27.3.</p>
            <p>But for a full <hi>Confirmation</hi> of it, <hi>God</hi> himſelf atteſted it in ſuch a manner, as <hi>ſufficiently</hi> ſhew'd his <hi>extream indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> againſt it, and <hi>conſign'd,</hi> to all <hi>ſucceeding Ages,</hi> his <hi>utter abhorrence</hi> and <hi>deteſtation</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> as a <hi>Crime</hi> of a moſt <hi>highly dreadful,</hi> and conſequently <hi>damning nature;</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, (as one obſerves) that ſome have <hi>ſmarted</hi> for it <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally,</hi> is for ever enough to <hi>convince</hi> us, that <hi>God</hi> is <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpeaſed</hi> with every one that thruſts <hi>himſelf</hi> into the <hi>guilt</hi> of it. But of theſe firſt <hi>Reſiſters,</hi> the <hi>Text</hi> tells us, <hi>That they went down alive into the Pit,</hi> according to our <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation;</hi> but the <hi>Margin</hi> reads into <hi>Hell,</hi> which <hi>Optatus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parmen</note> underſtands literally, <hi>Tartareo carcere ſubito clauſi:</hi> For certain to ſuch as follow their ſteps, St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith, <hi>Is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever,</hi> St. <hi>Jude</hi> 13. and St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays the ſame, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But a ſecond <hi>Inſtance</hi> is that of <hi>Samuel,</hi> who telling the <hi>People</hi> that had been <hi>importunate</hi> with him for a <hi>King</hi> to be ſet over them, after the manner of their <hi>Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations,</hi> when indeed they were under a <hi>Theocracy, God</hi> himſelf being <hi>immediately</hi> their <hi>King: Samuel,</hi> I ſay, telling them the manner of a <hi>King,</hi> in ſuch <hi>Inſtances</hi> as ſome will have to ſavour of an <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> tho' others reckon them only the <hi>neceſſary burdens</hi> and <hi>charges</hi> of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59325:15"/>However that be, the <hi>Prophet</hi> adds, that when they had once <hi>ſubjected</hi> themſelves to that <hi>Power,</hi> and felt themſelves <hi>aggrieved</hi> by it, they ſhould cry out in that day, becauſe of their <hi>King</hi> they had choſen them, and the <hi>Lord</hi> would not <hi>hear</hi> them in that <hi>day;</hi> it ſeems they ſhould have nothing left them, even in caſe of <hi>real grievance,</hi> but recourſe to <hi>God,</hi> and that would prove, in their caſe, <hi>ineffectual</hi> too, <hi>God</hi> would not hear them. But how if they ſhould take upon them to <hi>redreſs</hi> their <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances</hi> themſelves, by <hi>reſiſting</hi> and <hi>taking up Arms</hi> againſt their <hi>King?</hi> Why! it would only be <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>daringly</hi> to <hi>intrench</hi> upon God's <hi>Prerogative</hi> of <hi>Vengeance:</hi> But of that I leave you to <hi>conceive</hi> the <hi>iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But we have yet a <hi>plainer inſtance</hi> of the <hi>criminal na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting.</hi> 1 Sam. 26, where <hi>David</hi> having <hi>opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> which alone is oftentimes <hi>incentive</hi> enough in ſuch <hi>caſes,</hi> and <hi>abſolute Power</hi> to have deſtroy'd the <hi>King</hi> his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy,</hi> when 'tis certain he could as eaſily have taken away <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Life</hi> as his <hi>Spear,</hi> and we may ſuppoſe him <hi>promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> to it by two <hi>powerful motives, Interest</hi> and <hi>Revenge.</hi> And whatever there might be of <hi>guilt</hi> in it, <hi>Abiſhai</hi> offer'd to take that upon himſelf by <hi>perpetrating</hi> the <hi>fact,</hi> and laying <hi>violent hands</hi> upon <hi>Saul:</hi> Yet <hi>David</hi> would by no means ſuffer it, but urged this remarkable <hi>Query</hi> againſt it; <hi>Who can stretch forth his hand against the Lord's Anointed and be guiltleſs?</hi> But before whom ſhould <hi>David</hi> have been <hi>guilty?</hi> Or to whom <hi>accountable,</hi> if he had <hi>conſented?</hi> for he was (as I may ſay) <hi>Heir apparent</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> by <hi>Divine Deſignation:</hi> And was not the <hi>King</hi> his <hi>implacable Enemy,</hi> that had <hi>perſecuted</hi> him with the <hi>utmost</hi> of <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>virulency,</hi> againſt <hi>Law</hi> and againſt <hi>Reaſon?</hi> and had not God (as <hi>Abiſhai</hi> urged to him) delivered his <hi>Enemy</hi> into his hand, by caſting all his <hi>Army</hi> into a <hi>deep ſleep?</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:59325:15"/>and had <hi>cut them off,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> with <hi>them,</hi> Who ſhould have called <hi>David</hi> to an <hi>account</hi> for it?</p>
            <p>Why truly nothing of all this was in the leaſt to be feared in the <hi>Caſe:</hi> And yet <hi>David</hi> was <hi>infinitely afraid</hi> of <hi>ſtretching forth his hand against the Lords Anointed,</hi> or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another to do it, becauſe of the <hi>guilt</hi> attending it in the <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No!
<note place="margin">Homily of Obedience Part. II.</note> As the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> is in her <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi> concerning this very <hi>inſtance, David</hi> durſt not for fear of <hi>offending God</hi> and his <hi>own Conſcience</hi> (tho' he had <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> and <hi>opportunity</hi> for it) once lay his hand upon God's <hi>High Officer,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The King.</note> whom he did know to be a Perſon <hi>reſerved</hi> and <hi>kept</hi> for his <hi>Office-ſake</hi> only to God's <hi>Puniſhment</hi> and <hi>Judgment.</hi> And from this <hi>inſtance</hi> of <hi>David</hi>'s invincible <hi>Loyalty,</hi> ſo <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>manifeſt,</hi> ſo abundantly <hi>evident</hi> (one would think) beyond <hi>contradiction,</hi> the <hi>Homily</hi> aforeſaid infers, that it is an intolerable <hi>ignorance, madneſs</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> for <hi>Subjects</hi> to make any <hi>Murmuring, Rebellion, Reſiſtance,</hi> or <hi>Withſtanding, Commotion</hi> or <hi>Inſurrection</hi> againſt their moſt <hi>Dear</hi> and moſt <hi>Dread Sovereign Lord</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> ordained of God's <hi>Goodneſs</hi> for their <hi>Commodity, Peace</hi> and <hi>Quietneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we may judg of the <hi>Criminal nature</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> by God's <hi>ſevere proceedings</hi> againſt the <hi>Authors</hi> of it, What can we think, but that it is infinitely <hi>odious</hi> in his <hi>ſight?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>moſt</hi> remarkable <hi>inſtance</hi> of it he <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed</hi> by an aſtoniſhing <hi>Miracle,</hi> the Earth <hi>opening</hi> and <hi>ſwallowing</hi> up all the <hi>Reſiſters:</hi> And tho' 'tis true, nothing of this did ever happen <hi>again,</hi> yet that it did ſo <hi>once,</hi> is enough to aſſure us of God's <hi>eternal deteſtation</hi> of the <hi>Crime.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the next remarkable <hi>inſtance,</hi> I mean that of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> ſo ſtrangely infatuating the <hi>Counſels</hi> of the moſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59325:16"/>
               <hi>politick,</hi> and ſo <hi>amazingly</hi> bringing the miſerable <hi>Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader</hi> to his end, by making the <hi>Hair</hi> of his <hi>Head</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to his <hi>ruin,</hi> and cutting him off thus in the very <hi>act</hi> of his <hi>Crime,</hi> notwithſtanding all the <hi>care</hi> his <hi>Royal Father</hi> took to <hi>prevent</hi> it: Sure if we <hi>reflect</hi> ſeriouſly upon God's <hi>ſevere diſpleaſure,</hi> ſo ſignally <hi>evinced</hi> by ſuch <hi>aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtances</hi> of it, we cannot, with any <hi>ſhadow</hi> of <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> imagine that <hi>Reſiſting</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>light</hi> and <hi>trivial</hi> a matter, as ſome would fain have it from their <hi>fancied im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance</hi> of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in my <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, I would fain perſuade my ſelf, I have made it ſeem very <hi>probable,</hi> at leaſt, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this place of my <hi>Text,</hi> does really ſignifie <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> by what I have urged, 1. From the <hi>Context,</hi> which I am ſure very <hi>ſtrongly inclines</hi> to it, if I muſt not ſay <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely clears</hi> it. From the <hi>concurrent ſenſe</hi> of the moſt <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Expoſitors,</hi> as well <hi>Antient</hi> as <hi>Modern:</hi> And, 3. From <hi>parallel places</hi> of <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> which very <hi>plainly</hi> ſhew, that <hi>Reſiſting</hi> is a <hi>ſin</hi> exceedingly <hi>diſpleaſing,</hi> or rather <hi>deteſtable</hi> in the <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>conſequently,</hi> I may ſay, of a <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nature.</hi> I am ſure our <hi>Church</hi> is very <hi>clear</hi> for the <hi>damning nature</hi> of it,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ellion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ag. 379.</note> declaring in expreſs terms, <hi>that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Damnation is prepared for all impenitent Rebels in Hell with Satan, the first founder of Rebellion, and grand Captain of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels:</hi> And 'tis plain, that all <hi>Reſiſters</hi> with <hi>Her</hi> are <hi>Rebels.</hi> And the firſt <hi>Council</hi> that ever made any <hi>Canons</hi> againſt <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> was the fourth <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Toledo</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> Anno 633. for there never was any occaſion for the <hi>Churches proviſion</hi> againſt <hi>it</hi> before that, ſay ſome: For certain there was not, for the firſt three hundred and forty years, if not much longer. But that <hi>Council</hi> is very <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere</hi> againſt the <hi>Authors</hi> and <hi>Abettors</hi> of the <hi>Crime,</hi> not only <hi>Excommunicating</hi> and <hi>Anathematizing</hi> them, but <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59325:16"/>them to be <hi>damned</hi> in God's <hi>future Judgment,</hi> and to have their part with <hi>Judas Iſcariot:</hi> And this <hi>Sentence</hi> was confirmed in the Fifth <hi>Council</hi> that followed there, and the ſame was done in the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Calcuth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all, ſuppoſing it could not be made ſo <hi>clear</hi> as it may ſeem to be, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies in this place of my <hi>Text, eternal Damnation,</hi> without <hi>Repentance,</hi> yet what <hi>aſſurance</hi> can be given to any <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that makes the leaſt <hi>doubt</hi> or <hi>ſcruple</hi> whether it does not, when it cannot be deny'd but the word is <hi>capable</hi> of that <hi>ſenſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot <hi>conceive</hi> any other way of <hi>ſatisfying</hi> the <hi>doubt,</hi> or <hi>ſilencing</hi> the <hi>ſcruple,</hi> but one of theſe <hi>two;</hi> either a plain <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> or a new <hi>Revelation</hi> to the contrary.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>former</hi> of theſe, the matter is not <hi>capable</hi> of it: For who can pretend to <hi>Demonſtrate,</hi> or (to uſe a term of greater <hi>Latitude</hi>) undeniably <hi>convince</hi> any man living, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in this place, and by this word, did not mean <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the other way of a new <hi>Revelation,</hi> however the <hi>Perſon</hi> pretending to it may <hi>ſatisfie</hi> himſelf, he cannot another, of the <hi>truth</hi> of his <hi>Revelation</hi> without a <hi>Miracle,</hi> or ſomewhat equivalent to <hi>attest</hi> it: And without that, what <hi>ſecurity</hi> can he give that he does not <hi>incur</hi> that <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> againſt <hi>Angel</hi> or <hi>Man</hi> that ſhould <hi>Preach</hi> another <hi>Goſpel,</hi> or the contrary to that he had <hi>Preached?</hi> Gal. 1.8, 9.</p>
            <p>And without ſuch <hi>Conviction,</hi> as either that of <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,</hi> or a new <hi>Revelation</hi> ſufficiently <hi>atteſted,</hi> what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite <hi>hazard</hi> is it for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to venture upon the <hi>guilt</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> which, 'tis more than <hi>poſſible,</hi> for <hi>certain</hi> may be attended with <hi>Damnation in the ſaddest ſenſe?</hi> I am pretty ſure there is no abſolute <hi>ſecurity</hi> againſt it, in caſe of actual <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> but <hi>Repentance</hi> only: And that muſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59325:17"/>be granted infinitely <hi>hazardous</hi> in a <hi>War,</hi> eſpecially if the <hi>War</hi> be ſinful.</p>
            <p>And for a <hi>Perſon</hi> to be taken away ſuddenly by <hi>death,</hi> in the very <hi>act</hi> of <hi>Reſiſting,</hi> as 'tis <hi>poſſible,</hi> yea, <hi>probable;</hi> nay, let me add, 'tis very great odds but he may, if <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged</hi> in it, and at his firſt appearance before the grand <hi>Tribunal,</hi> hear the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> or his <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> avouch, that by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this place, was truly meant <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the ſaddest ſenſe,</hi> is infinitely <hi>aſtoniſhing,</hi> and much too <hi>dreadful</hi> in <hi>Theory,</hi> ever to be <hi>hazarded</hi> in <hi>Practice</hi> by rational <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that does indeed <hi>believe,</hi> and has any tolerable <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of <hi>Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well! but ſuppoſing the worſt, Is there nothing to take off the <hi>force</hi> of this <hi>intermination?</hi> No lawful <hi>ground</hi> of <hi>reſiſting</hi> the <hi>Higher Powers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, not any, as I come to ſhew, according to my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Propoſal;</hi> namely, that there is no juſt caſe of <hi>excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> againſt the <hi>rule</hi> of my <hi>Text,</hi> no pretence <hi>allowable:</hi> But for <hi>Subjects</hi> to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> I mean, <hi>forcibly</hi> to <hi>reſist</hi> their <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sovereign,</hi> is <hi>abſolutely</hi> and <hi>univerſally</hi> to incur <hi>Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and nothing to <hi>atone</hi> for the <hi>crime</hi> in the <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or to prevent the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> threatned here, but <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs this <hi>aſſertion</hi> cannot but ſeem a little <hi>ſtrange,</hi> when there have been ſo many caſes of <hi>exception</hi> made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this <hi>general Rule,</hi> ſo many <hi>pretences</hi> ſet on <hi>foot,</hi> and reckon'd <hi>allowable,</hi> ſo many <hi>ſtarting holes</hi> found out.</p>
            <p>But I am ſure I have very good <hi>Authority</hi> for what I ſay, our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> as well as <hi>Canons,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> being clear on my ſide: And this methinks ſhould ſeem, in all <hi>reaſon,</hi> abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſufficient</hi> to any profeſſed <hi>Member</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> who muſt neceſſarily <hi>renounce</hi> ſuch his <hi>Memberſhip,</hi> and ceaſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59325:17"/>to be of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> before he can allow himſelf the liberty of <hi>reſiſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for our Laws, that of the 25 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and thoſe of the 13 &amp; 14 of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, declare it univerſally unlawful to make or levy any war againſt the King, without the allowance of any caſe or pretence whatſoever; and the ſame is expreſly required to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all the Clergy in the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> and the ſame in ſubſtance is required of all Civil and Military Officers.</p>
            <p>Our Canons declare expreſly againſt all taking up of Arms, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offenſive or defenſive, without the Royal Authority, much more againſt it, upon any pretence whatſoever, under pain of <hi>Damnation,</hi> for which they cite the words of my Text, as very plain in their ſenſe.
<note n="*" place="margin">The firſt of the <hi>Canons</hi> of 1640.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our Homilies teach us, God hath ſhewn that he alloweth neither the Dignity of any Perſon, nor the Multitude of any Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor the Weight of any Cauſe, as ſufficient for the which Subjects may move Rebellion againſt their Princes.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Homily</hi> againſt <hi>Rebellion,</hi> p. 368.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It were endleſs to cite particular Writers of our Church to this purpoſe; but by what has been ſaid, ſo clear is the Doctrine of our Church in the point, as ſome have made this remark upon it, That ſince the Reformation it is now again current <hi>Epiſcopal Doctrine,</hi> as it was always <hi>Apoſtolical, That Subjects ought by no means to reſiſt, nor can be diſobliged from their Obedience to their Sovereigns, upon any pretence whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being then ſo clearly the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that confirm'd or back'd by the Civil Sanction, and ſo the avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſenſe of all the Authority of the Nation; is it not prodigiouſly ſtrange to hear it excepted againſt, not only by <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, but, what is much more, by pretended Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as we have had, ſome few years paſt, ſufficient evidence?</p>
            <p>Well! but does the Church of <hi>England</hi> agree in the point with the Church of Chriſt in the primitive and pureſt ages of it? or with other Churches of the Reformation?</p>
            <p>That it does perfectly agree with the primitive Church in the point, has been ſo frequently, ſo plainly, and ſo convincingly proved, that the Oppugners of it have been forced to have recourſe either to down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Slandering and Lying, or elſe to Enthuſiaſm.</p>
            <p>To the firſt, affirming, contrary to the faith of antient and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Hiſtories, and all accounts of thoſe times, that the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> then generally maintain'd, and the practice of Chriſtians
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59325:18"/>exactly ſuited thereto, was grounded upon nothing elſe but weakneſs, or want of ſtrength: they did not reſiſt <hi>quia deerant vires,</hi> as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> leads the Dance, and 'tis incredible how he is followed.</p>
            <p>But in anſwer to it, 1. <hi>admitting,</hi> but by no means <hi>granting,</hi> that want of ſtrength or forces was one ground of their conſtant Loyalty, without the leaſt attempt of reſiſting; yet what an abominable ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is it to ſay, (which yet is ſaid) that it was the <hi>only ground</hi> of it, when their Apologiſts and other eminent Writers, lay down unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reaſons why they <hi>would not, did not, durſt not reſiſt,</hi> even becauſe they thought themſelves obliged to ſuffer any thing from the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, rather than reſiſt, by the moſt ſacred and indiſpenſable Laws of their Religion, as hath been very often, and of late abundantly made appear. Want of ſtrength then was not the <hi>only ground</hi> of their not reſiſting, as ſome have ſhamefully ſlander'd them: And no wonder, when others have not ſtuck to ſpeak as ſlanderouſly of the Apoſtles themſelves, as if their end in preſcribing Subjection and Obedience at firſt, were only to flatter the Emperours, and curry favour with them, as <hi>Salmeron</hi> had the impudence to affirm.</p>
            <p>But, 2. that want of ſtrength or forces was any ground or reaſon at all of their not reſiſting, is ſo far from truth, that there never was a more ſilly groundleſs falſity invented, as hath been invincibly made appear to the meaneſt capacities, and therefore I ſhall the leſs need to inſiſt upon it. But I beg leave to urge two things with reference to it: The one is an inſtance not ſo commonly taken notice of, and that is this; In the Reign of <hi>Adrian</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> almoſt univerſally, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially about <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Cyrene,</hi> rebell'd againſt the Emperour, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in Arms under <hi>Barchochebas</hi> their Leader, to the number of ſome hundred thouſands; and much about the ſame time, as may be gather'd from <hi>Euſebius,</hi> there was a Perſecution on foot againſt the Chriſtians, which might have prompted them to joyn with thoſe <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rebels; and that they might have joyned with them if they would, is too certain, when they were uſed with at leaſt as much cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and ſavageneſs by the Rebels, meerly becauſe they would not joyn with them, as ever they had been by any of their Perſecutors, and yet they could never be drawn, by arts or arguments, by perſuaſion or force, to aſſociate with the Rebels. And this inſtance ſeems to me ſo plain and home to the purpoſe, that I ſhall only make this remark upon it, That thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the late Times were not the firſt Martyrs or Confeſſors purely for Loyalty, theſe primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians being their Precedents, and leading them the way.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59325:18"/>
            <p>The other thing I have to urge in the caſe, is this; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and his followers, in very great numbers affirm, That the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians wanted ſtrength or forces to reſiſt: but <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who lived in thoſe times, ſays, <hi>They filled all places but the Temples, and were of all the ſtanding Offices almoſt in the whole Empire.</hi> And St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> not long after him, affirms, <hi>That they were vaſtly numerous and copious;</hi> that is, as the word ſeems to import, they were of the Militia or Souldiery too. And 'tis undeniably evident, that almoſt all <hi>Julian</hi>'s Army when he died were Chriſtians, as the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtorians all with one mouth aſſert. Now, whether you will believe <hi>Tertullian</hi> and St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and ſo many antient Hiſtorians, or <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and his followers, is left to your choice.</p>
            <p>But the prettieſt that has been ſaid upon this caſe of reſiſtance, and St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine about it, is this, that <hi>Paul</hi> intended his Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance purely with reſpect to the men he wrote to, of that Age 'tis meant, and no otherwiſe than as if a man ſhould write to the Chriſtians at preſent under the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominion, confeſſedly poor, and unable indeed to reſiſt him; would he not write as <hi>Paul</hi> did? No que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but this learned Author fully knew the Apoſtle's mind: nay, and had conſulted him perſonally upon the point, when he ſo confidently adds, <hi>That if</hi> Paul <hi>were alive, and ſaw wicked Kings reigning in Chriſtian Commonwealths, he would leave them to their Subjects to be puniſhed by them without blame.</hi> Whither are we rapt now? into the third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, there to conſult <hi>Paul?</hi> But I told you recourſe was to be had of neceſſity either to downright ſtandering and lying, or elſe to Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſm; and here ſeems to be ſomewhat of both.</p>
            <p>But this was the familiar mode of the late Times to pretend Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: So <hi>John Goodwin; Now that Antichriſt is apparently come to his full Power and Authority, that which was not known before, but kept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd from the Churches of Chriſt, is fully manifeſt, that Chriſtians may lawfully, in a lawful way,</hi> (that is when they may lawfully) <hi>ſtand up to defend themſelves, in caſe they be able, againſt any unlawful aſſaults, by what aſſailants, or by what pretended Authority ſoever, made upon them.</hi> And another, <hi>The lawfulneſs of Rebellion is now diſcovered to God's Church as the neceſſary means to ruin Antichriſt:</hi> So <hi>Burroughs</hi> cants af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Goodwin.</hi> But a more blunt Enthuſiaſt has told us roundly, <hi>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was God's will the primitive Chriſtians ſhould confirm the truth by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, but now that it is confirm'd, his will is that we ſhould defend the truth by action, in deſtroying Tyrants.</hi> Boldly ſaid indeed, and methinks this Gentleman ſeems more intimately acquainted with God himſelf,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59325:19"/>than the former was with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as knowing God's ſecret will, for we know of nothing he has revealed but the contrary to this as his will in the caſe.</p>
            <p>But to leave Enthuſiaſts as paſt conviction, and to have as little regard to thoſe others who have the impudence to oppoſe a known certain truth, as clear as any thing of that nature can poſſibly be, with meer ſhams, I ſay the Doctrine of the Primitive Church is plain and manifeſt againſt all Reſiſting upon any pretence whatſoever, ſo plain and clear, that as was before obſerv'd, not one writer for a thouſand years of any Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the Church did ever queſtion it; And <hi>Sigebert</hi> reckon'd the contrary doctrine a novelty at leaſt, if not a plain Hereſie, and juſtly imputes the original of it to Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> as not crept into the World before him.</p>
            <p>As for the Churches of the Reformation, they are no leſs plain and clear againſt all reſiſting, as any man may ſatisfie himſelf from their general confeſſions, and from the writings of particular members of them: I ſhall only urge the Authority of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> who though he liv'd and dy'd in the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet was for a Reformation, and according to ſome the occaſion of it; and I the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſiſt upon his Authority, becauſe his Comments are recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our own Reformers, and ordered to be had in all our Churches: Now he in his Comment upon St. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. affirms, there is no He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie more pernitious than this of the lawfulneſs of reſiſting: the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Chriſt decrying it, his whole life being oppoſite to it, the Apoſtolical Doctrine teſtifying againſt it, it being rejected alſo by ſo many thouſand Martyrs, and contradicted by the Antient Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: I may add, by all impartial writers of the Reformation.</p>
            <p>And this ſure cannot but ſeem abundantly ſufficient to all unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd minds, that ſincerely deſire to know the truth, and are willing to be convinced of it.</p>
            <p>Let me have leave to add this, as which makes very much for my Aſſertion of the abſolute unlawfulneſs of reſiſting, that the Caſes of Exception are ſo very wild and extravagant: and but two of them are worth taking notice of. As for the Additional ones of <hi>Grotius,</hi> 'tis ſaid, he was young when he made them, and 'tis plain he was to ſerve an argument, having his Country-men to defend.</p>
            <p>As for that of Religion, which ſome inſiſt on, as not only a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but the very beſt ground of reſiſting, 'tis the moſt ſenſeleſs impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition upon the common reaſon of mankind that can well be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd, to pretend it: for who knows not that our Religion can never
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59325:19"/>be loſt or taken from us by all the Powers of Earth and Hell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin'd together againſt us, without our own conſent. But what do I talk of Religion in the Caſe? that's commonly no more than the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face or ſhell; 'tis Ambition, or Intereſt, or Revenge is the Kernel or Subſtance, for without ſuch mixtures, Religion (as a Learned Gentleman obſerves
<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>William Temple,</hi> p. 57.</note>) works no violent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, but produces rather examples of conſtant ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than of deſperate actions. To pretend Religion therefore as a ground of reſiſting, is only to make appear our hypocriſie: which <hi>Harry Martin</hi> honeſtly diſclaim'd when he cry'd out in the houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſnivelling for Religion, as the ground of reſiſting the King: <hi>We have fought</hi> (ſays he) <hi>all this while for Liberty, and are we now whining about Religion?</hi> And one <hi>Colonel Purefoy,</hi> like another <hi>Peribo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> was much more ingenious, declaring plainly after the King was beheaded, <hi>that it was no more than what he had deſir'd, and deſigned to contribute to, forty years before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtill, as I ſaid, there are two caſes of exception inſiſted on, as of ſome validity. 1. If a Prince ſhall undertake to alienate his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or ſell it, or give it up into the hands of another Sovereign, againſt the mind of his Subjects. A very pritty ſuppoſition, but only that it is ſo very unreaſonable, as not to be ſuppoſed by all the rules of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mom prudence or charity: beſides, that it may be always pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if once ſuffered to paſs, and where are we then? Why then we are at the old paſs of undermining the <hi>Thames:</hi> that is of having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the moſt ridiculous and incredible ſtories obtruded upon us, and we muſt believe them for the good of the Common-wealth, which otherwiſe would be in mighty danger. Well! but there is another caſe of exception, rather more unreaſonable than the former, and yet, at the leaſt, as likely to be always pretended, and that is: If a Prince ſhall undertake to deſtroy his whole Kingdom, or any conſiderable part of it.</p>
            <p>The former of theſe, beſides, that it very reverendly ſuppoſes the Prince either a fool or a madman, is little better than non-ſenſe, and next to impoſſible at leaſt. But the latter, that a Prince ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a conſiderable part of his Subjects, was plainly the caſe of the Primitive Chriſtians, who were certainly both for number and quality, but eſpecially, for number, a very conſiderable part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, <hi>pars major Civitatis cujuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) the greater part of every City: and according to <hi>Grotius, metu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda plane multitudo</hi> in plain Engliſh formidable for their numbers:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59325:20"/>yet they were not only deſign'd to utter deſtruction, but actually deſtroy'd in vaſt infinite numbers, by the expreſs order of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Emperours, and that with the utmoſt cruelty and ſavageneſs, contrary to all the rules of nature, reaſon, and humanity. And yet, ſtill among theſe, <hi>qui ipſorum ſaevitiae arma opponeret inventus eſt nemo</hi> (ſays <hi>Grotius</hi>) and it has been ſufficiently ſhewed already: not one was found that wou'd oppoſe their Cruelty by force of Arms. Not one? Yes, ſays <hi>Blondel,</hi> I have found two inſtances to the contrary. And the truth is, he has two inſtances, but they are both wondrous odd: As that of a company of drunken Villagers, very probably Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans too, reſcuing <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> from the hands of his Proſecutors, who were but private Souldiers neither: and the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians</hi> reſiſting <hi>Maximin</hi> who was not their Sovereign. Which only ſhew the good mans earneſt deſire to have them pertinent, whether they will be ſo or no.</p>
            <p>But after all, there are Scripture inſtances produced to the contrary of this Aſſertion, that it is abſolutely unlawful to reſiſt.</p>
            <p>And 'tis true, there are Scripture inſtances alledged, but no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as Texts of Scripture are by ſome quoted, only to make a flouriſh withall, and fill up a margin, or to ſeem proofs, though hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſhadow of them.</p>
            <p>And as for theſe inſtances out of Scripture, they have been conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and ſufficiently prov'd to be either impertinent as ſome, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary as others, or laſtly wicked, and ſo not to be brought into example. And they do but only ſhew how hard the Oppugners of this Doctrine are put to it, when they can produce no better for their purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And now to come home to our ſelves, and very briefly to apply what has been ſaid. The charge here againſt Reſiſting is Univerſal, and there is no limitation of it in the whole Scripture, none in the old Teſtament, much leſs in the new, and leaſt of all in this Chapter where the rule is laid: and beſides, the context or the Analogy of the place, the conſent of ſundry, the moſt eminent and learned expoſitours both antient and modern, and the practice of the beſt Chriſtians in all ages have been ſhewn very clear for the abſolute un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of reſiſting upon what pretence ſoever under pain of <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And ſure, if to reſiſt the higher powers be (as the Apoſtle aſſerts in general) to reſiſt the Ordinance of God, it is <hi>eo nomine,</hi> in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect alone ſo far from lawful in any caſe, or upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that it is infallibly always a ſin of a moſt provoking nature,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59325:20"/>and as ſuch it is here threatned, as far as I can poſſibly conceive or underſtand with <hi>Damnation</hi> in the ſaddeſt ſenſe. And let me ſay <hi>Damnation</hi> is not to be trifled with, nor the Apoſtle's fearful threat here eluded by ſlights and pretences; but be theſe what they will, if upon them we reſiſt, we muſt ceaſe to be Chriſtians, ceaſe to be of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ceaſe to be in a ſaveable condition, unleſs a very great and ſolemn Repentance intervene.</p>
            <p>But for that, beſides, that it is always infinitely hazardous in caſe of reſiſting, ſuch is the criminal nature of reſiſting, that the Scripture compares it to Witchcraft, and indeed it too nearly reſembles the ſin of Witchcraft in this reſpect, (not that it admits not of Repentance, for I will not ſay ſo of its parallel, but) that it is ſeldom at all, and ſeldomer truly repented of; and for this I ſhall ſeek no further than our own age and memory: with what a wild Enthuſiaſm did the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Cromwel</hi> go to his own place? What an opinion had he of his Saintſhip to the very laſt? as if he were one of thoſe that needed no Repentance. When his end apparently drew near, he wou'd not be perſwaded of it, but ſtill fancied to himſelf that God had ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther work in reſerve for him. And his Brethren in iniquity and bloud, the Regicides that were executed, with what height of Fanaticiſm went they out of the World? how far from the leaſt ſhew of Repentance? And oh bleſſed God! how few publick Recantations have we ſeen, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſo very many were engaged in the <hi>Great Rebellion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they were, they were the Saints; and as ſuch I leave them, to beſpeak your utter abhorrence and deteſtation of a Crime, which by what has been ſaid may reaſonably be concluded, or at leaſt juſtly feared, to be of a moſt horrid nature, expoſing to <hi>Damnation</hi> in the ſaddeſt ſenſe. And let us conſider the fearful iſſues of <hi>Damnation,</hi> and the infinite uncertainty of Repentance, which alone can prevent them in caſe of reſiſting. And as we would not loſe our part with God, our ſhare in the Joys and Glories of Jeſus, our habitation in the Heavens with Angels and Saints in unſpeakable happineſs to eternal ages, which is the firſt ſad part of <hi>Damnation.</hi> And then for the other, as we would not be given up to the inſupportable amazements of a ſad Eternity, and dwell with a Worm that dieth not, in a Fire that is not quenched, amidſt Devils and damned Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits for ever; let us beware of reſiſting the Higher Powers, which is a crime that expoſes to all this, and more. But let us heartily bleſs Almighty God that we had no ſhare in the great Rebellion, no
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59325:21"/>hand in the <hi>Thirtieth of January,</hi> nothing to do but to bewail our own ſins as <hi>acceſſary,</hi> and the ſins of others as <hi>inſtrumental</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>And for the mercy of this <hi>Auſpicious Day</hi> to the Church ſtill flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, though the Prince for whoſe <hi>Birth and Return</hi> it was ſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable, be gone; and may it flouriſh ſtill, as we have juſt ground to hope it will, under his excellent Parallel, our preſent gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, whom God long preſerve. I ſay, for the mercy of this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious Day,</hi> let us be ſure to render now and ever, as is both now and ever abundantly due, to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, all poſſible Praiſe, Honour, and Thankſgiving, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
